<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>meta on eval/apply</title><link>/tags/meta/</link><description>Recent content in meta on eval/apply</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2022 10:24:39 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/meta/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Baby don't hurry, don't stop (feat. Melancholy)</title><link>/posts/dont-hurry-dont-stop-sad-version/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2022 10:24:39 +0530</pubDate><guid>/posts/dont-hurry-dont-stop-sad-version/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is how I struggle from time to time. It is not pretty. These days it&amp;rsquo;s
been a lot more. Thankfully, it is not a constant. Instead of reading this,
you should want to listen to Alain de Botton.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Aw1oLtuJOXQ">on Pessimism&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jJ6K%5Ff7oSdg">on Love&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=W9X7u-MeJz0">on an Emotional Education&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>For here lies melancholy that I put to paper from a particularly deep hole,
not too long ago. It may ruin your day, or it may make you feel a little bit
understood about your dark moments. And it&amp;mdash;unlike Alain&amp;rsquo;s teachings&amp;mdash;will
certainly not help you find a way through.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Your mileage &lt;em>will&lt;/em> vary.&lt;/p></description><content>&lt;p>This is how I struggle from time to time. It is not pretty. These days it&amp;rsquo;s
been a lot more. Thankfully, it is not a constant. Instead of reading this,
you should want to listen to Alain de Botton.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Aw1oLtuJOXQ">on Pessimism&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jJ6K%5Ff7oSdg">on Love&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=W9X7u-MeJz0">on an Emotional Education&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>For here lies melancholy that I put to paper from a particularly deep hole,
not too long ago. It may ruin your day, or it may make you feel a little bit
understood about your dark moments. And it&amp;mdash;unlike Alain&amp;rsquo;s teachings&amp;mdash;will
certainly not help you find a way through.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Your mileage &lt;em>will&lt;/em> vary.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Today was one of those days.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When the feeling hit like a slap in the face. Again. Just how much of my
youth burned in self-doubt, fear, self-shame, akrasia.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Twenty years of young adulthood incinerated by mine own hand, before my own
eyes, and I did nothing to save it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sigh.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This life is singular. It is not ours to have. It is not ours to end. It is
ours to embrace as a gift to give away.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The gift is a chance to become all that we can become. We cannot become, if we
keep staring down at ourselves from imagined imaginations of others. What if
I can&amp;rsquo;t do it? What if I fail? What if nobody likes me? I am not &lt;em>this&lt;/em>. I am
not &lt;em>that&lt;/em>. I&amp;rsquo;ll never get &lt;em>there&lt;/em>. &lt;em>I&lt;/em> am not even someone. That is the root
of all self-doubt and fear and shame. A never-being in the here and now. A
never-learning about oneself. A never-knowing of feeling alive. The kind of
poverty that material things cannot end.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Looking from the outside makes us pressure and twist ourselves into the imagined
mould. But the mould changes before we&amp;rsquo;re done. And we start again. The cycle is
endless, relentless. We go faster, but it changes faster. And we forget ourselves.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If there is one gift we can give to another, especially a young one, it would
be to show them how to live this: &amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t hurry, don&amp;rsquo;t stop.&amp;rdquo;. To learn to &lt;em>do&lt;/em>,
without fearing the unknown, knowing failure without shame, with kindness, with
oneself, without hurry.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Hurry forces pause. Not pausing breaks us. So many break forever. Never becoming.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So many learn too late, that they only know to hurry, that they can&amp;rsquo;t slow down.
Once perhaps, long ago, they peered inside their mould and saw nothing. It&amp;rsquo;s
not that nothing exists, it&amp;rsquo;s that they never learned to see. And so all that
remained was to dwell in the future; remoulding faster and faster until the
breakdown. Or worse, to delve into the past, in endless revisions of discarded
moulds to reach an imagined now that never will come to pass. If there is a
metaverse, it is this.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This prisoners' game of imagined imaginations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Fantasies rooted in fantasy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s not too late for you. Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s not too late for me.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I hope it isn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But if it is too late, then I hope we come back, you and I.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For a rebirth requires a death.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;em>“It is better to do something continuously, perpetually and untiringly than to hustle and fail.”&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>“If you hurry, you must rest. If you want to keep going without resting, then you mustn’t hurry.”&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>“Don’t hurry, don’t stop”&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kintar%C5%8D%5FHattori">Kintarō Hattori&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote></content></item><item><title>How To Be a Totally Natural Conference Speaker?</title><link>/posts/how-to-give-a-conference-talk/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2022 01:56:02 +0530</pubDate><guid>/posts/how-to-give-a-conference-talk/</guid><description>&lt;p>A friend and I were chatting recently about speaking at conferences. Now this
person is smart and I&amp;rsquo;ve learned a thing or two from his in-depth engineering
blog posts. Yet there he was, telling me I&amp;rsquo;m so super good at communicating
ideas (implying he&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>not&lt;/em> so super good), and besides he has nothing to say
worthy of a conference talk.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Huh?!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Uncalled for praise is jarring, but I took it&amp;mdash;2021 was heartless, OK? Still,
the subtext of &lt;em>magic&lt;/em> bothered me. That I am somehow special. A born natural.
So I told him my secret formula. And now I&amp;rsquo;m telling you.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here is how to be a totes natural conference speaker&amp;hellip;&lt;/p></description><content>&lt;p>A friend and I were chatting recently about speaking at conferences. Now this
person is smart and I&amp;rsquo;ve learned a thing or two from his in-depth engineering
blog posts. Yet there he was, telling me I&amp;rsquo;m so super good at communicating
ideas (implying he&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>not&lt;/em> so super good), and besides he has nothing to say
worthy of a conference talk.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Huh?!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Uncalled for praise is jarring, but I took it&amp;mdash;2021 was heartless, OK? Still,
the subtext of &lt;em>magic&lt;/em> bothered me. That I am somehow special. A born natural.
So I told him my secret formula. And now I&amp;rsquo;m telling you.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here is how to be a totes natural conference speaker&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Mope around &lt;em>all the time&lt;/em> about how you don&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em>really&lt;/em> know [Topic X].
Sooner or later an opportune Call For Proposals will slide into your Twitter
stream or Slack or Discord. (It is very important to mope around &lt;em>all&lt;/em> the
time. Also, please cultivate several topics to mope around about. This
guarantees that every moment is an opportune moment to propose a talk.)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Foolishly jump at the chance. Write a proposal to talk (or teach a class)
about said [Topic X].&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Congratulations! You have now made a public commitment, and opted into the
specter of falling flat on your face before all and sundry. Let the feeling
sink in.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>When it does, panic and feel obligated to start making something already,
because what if you can&amp;rsquo;t actually figure out [Topic X]? Because then you
must recuse yourself before it&amp;rsquo;s too late. Proceed to have trouble starting,
toss and turn in bed many nights in a row, and finally start typing
something&amp;mdash;anything&amp;mdash;into your computer.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Make and trash at least 3 shitty first drafts. Feel like an impostor and
&lt;em>almost&lt;/em> withdraw your proposal as many times.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>If your proposal gets selected, GOTO 3 and start over. If it doesn&amp;rsquo;t, GOTO 8.
If you are back here after the do-over, GOTO 7. If you got here and you don&amp;rsquo;t
know why, well that&amp;rsquo;s because GOTOs are Considered Harmful.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Somehow arrive at a version you don&amp;rsquo;t totally hate. Then make minor edits
and tweaks for days and days until you&amp;rsquo;re fed up. (Actually you are fed up
because the talk is just a week away by now, and you haven&amp;rsquo;t rehearsed even
once.)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Corral friends who are way smarter than you, and get them to hear you out.
(Actually there&amp;rsquo;s a step zero. Get very lucky in life and land up with such
friends).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Listen to them and don&amp;rsquo;t make any more edits.&lt;/em> Seriously. Try to rehearse.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Second-guess yourself 48 hours before your talk, mid-way through your first
&lt;em>actual&lt;/em> rehearsal. Proceed to commit the cardinal sin of refactoring the
whole bloody thing &amp;ldquo;before shipping to production&amp;rdquo;, because apparently it&amp;rsquo;s
all completely &lt;em>wrong&lt;/em> now. Don&amp;rsquo;t sleep much, of course.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Wake up with a start on D-day. Curse at yourself in the mirror. Drink an
unconscionable quantity of coffee, while feverishly reviewing your material.
Entirely miss the &amp;ldquo;hallway track&amp;rdquo; and fail to make new friends or to have
a good time.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Somehow make it to the other end of your presentation. It&amp;rsquo;s OK, everybody
forgets half the material (especially those painstakingly crafted turns of
phrase and clever asides), and still somehow runs out of time. Spend the
rest of the day in a growing fog because the adrenaline wore off, but the
caffeine didn&amp;rsquo;t, but you&amp;rsquo;re wiped-out from the excitement and sleep-deprived.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Luckily, that also means you forget everything you did on your talk day.
Now you just have to make sure you never ever watch the recording of your
talk, if they publish it.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Bask in the certain knowledge that you too have become a 100% Totally Natural
Conference Speaker. (As a veteran of this process, I can tell you it works.
Every. Single. Time.)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Jokes apart, it really is like that. There is no magic. Only student syndrome.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Just remember that you always know more about something than someone, and/or
almost certainly have a &lt;em>different, unique take&lt;/em> on something that you believe
to be common knowledge. Not infrequently, I find someone&amp;rsquo;s interpretation of
something I am intimately familiar with, and the interpretation remarkably
changes how I see/feel/understand/relate with the thing. (Frequently it does
not, and it&amp;rsquo;s rubbish, but that&amp;rsquo;s fine. I&amp;rsquo;m not the one for that one.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Why? Well because no topic is objectively too small or too silly or too useless,
for the right audience in the right context.
Look no further than &lt;a href="https://bangbangcon.com/program.html">!!Con&lt;/a>, for example.
People have i!!ega! amounts of fun there!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So do yourself a favour. Allow yourself chances to suggest your [Topic X] to
the world, even when it&amp;rsquo;s just your take on your favourite thing that maybe
everybody already knows. Because maybe the world will say&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Sure, why not?&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>