<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>meta on eval/apply</title><link>/tags/meta/</link><description>Recent content in meta on eval/apply</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2022 01:15:15 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/meta/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>What makes Functional Programming and/or Functional Systems "Functional"?</title><link>/posts/what-makes-functional-programming-systems-functional/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2022 01:15:15 +0530</pubDate><guid>/posts/what-makes-functional-programming-systems-functional/</guid><description>&lt;p>In which we ponder the Functional Nature of Life, The Universe, and Everything.
Please feel free to follow through the weeds, or jump straight to the bottom
for my 2 nano BTC on the matter. (Or my current state of mind, at any rate.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Disclaimer: I live in the Land of Lisp, meditate in the Church of Alonzo, and
am ever-wary of The State. Only converts &lt;em>might&lt;/em> find some entertainment value.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;em>&amp;ldquo;For the love of State is the root of all evil: which while some coveted after,&lt;/em>
&lt;em>they have erred from Lambda the Ultimate, and pierced themselves through with&lt;/em>
&lt;em>many sorrows.&amp;quot;&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#is-it-already-suffusing-your-very-being">Is it already suffusing your very being?&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#is-it-mathematics">Is it Mathematics?&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#is-it-being-declarative">Is it being &amp;ldquo;declarative&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#is-it-being-data-oriented">Is it being &amp;ldquo;data-oriented&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#is-it-about-statelessness">Is it about &amp;ldquo;Statelessness&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#is-it-about-managed-environments">Is it about &amp;ldquo;managed&amp;rdquo; environments?&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#is-it-about-following-some-discipline-and-maybe-automating-it">Is it about following some discipline, and maybe automating it?&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#my-2-nano-btc-on-the-matter">My 2 nano BTC on the matter&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --></description><content>&lt;p>In which we ponder the Functional Nature of Life, The Universe, and Everything.
Please feel free to follow through the weeds, or jump straight to the bottom
for my 2 nano BTC on the matter. (Or my current state of mind, at any rate.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Disclaimer: I live in the Land of Lisp, meditate in the Church of Alonzo, and
am ever-wary of The State. Only converts &lt;em>might&lt;/em> find some entertainment value.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;em>&amp;ldquo;For the love of State is the root of all evil: which while some coveted after,&lt;/em>
&lt;em>they have erred from Lambda the Ultimate, and pierced themselves through with&lt;/em>
&lt;em>many sorrows.&amp;quot;&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#is-it-already-suffusing-your-very-being">Is it already suffusing your very being?&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#is-it-mathematics">Is it Mathematics?&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#is-it-being-declarative">Is it being &amp;ldquo;declarative&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#is-it-being-data-oriented">Is it being &amp;ldquo;data-oriented&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#is-it-about-statelessness">Is it about &amp;ldquo;Statelessness&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#is-it-about-managed-environments">Is it about &amp;ldquo;managed&amp;rdquo; environments?&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#is-it-about-following-some-discipline-and-maybe-automating-it">Is it about following some discipline, and maybe automating it?&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#my-2-nano-btc-on-the-matter">My 2 nano BTC on the matter&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="is-it-already-suffusing-your-very-being">Is it already suffusing your very being?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Because so-called &amp;ldquo;Functional Programming&amp;rdquo; started becoming pretty sexy over
the 2010s. By the 2020s, it started infiltrating all the things, small and big
and hyperscaled.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Now you can&amp;rsquo;t get people to shut up about their declarative infrastructure-as-code
as-YAML microservices-first infinitely elastic shared-nothing event-sourced
map-reducing lambda architecture marvels.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Now your VCs and your board nod sagely when these words flash past in your slick
OKR plan vision strategy slide decks. Now they further &lt;em>&amp;ldquo;Hey, quick question&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em>
you to same-page on your strategy for blockchain and smart contracts. And
general web3 readiness. So does every novice hire it seems, no matter their role.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Now&amp;mdash;and be honest, OK?&amp;mdash;don&amp;rsquo;t you feel like everybody should just mentally
lie down for a few minutes in their metaverse, pass around the meta-ayahuasca,
and after the purge just ask simple meta-questions about FP and life for a
change? Because, for the love of lambda, we haven&amp;rsquo;t even gotten a breather
from the fast-nearing AI supremacy?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>No? OK, consider the following incomplete list of traits commonly attributed
to the &amp;ldquo;Functional&amp;rdquo; paradigm of programming languages and of systems. Alongside,
consider:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Which traits does your pet programming language (or system) provide by default?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Which traits do you create yourself in your programs (and systems)?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Which traits draw the hard line between &amp;ldquo;Functional&amp;rdquo; and other kinds of
programs (and systems)?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Which traits &lt;em>really&lt;/em> matter?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Why would you even want any of it in the first place?&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>And will we really achieve world domination with FP? (Yes, we will.)&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="is-it-mathematics">Is it Mathematics?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Is it about writing &amp;ldquo;pure&amp;rdquo; functions?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is a bit of a tautology. A function is &amp;ldquo;pure&amp;rdquo; by definition. It specifies
a fixed mapping of an input domain to an output domain. When invoked, it
changes nothing about the state of the world. Which begs the question, how can
a thing that &lt;em>does&lt;/em> nothing be computationally useful? (Spoiler: it isn&amp;rsquo;t in
isolation, unless of course, you figure out a way to use the computational
uselessness to turn staggeringly larger amounts of electricity into progressively
smaller fragments of your imagination, on a blockchain somewhere). But I digress&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Must we further also have &amp;ldquo;first-class&amp;rdquo; functions?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ones that we can pass around as values? This lets us describe all manner of
deferred computations, including un-computable absurdities like infinite sequences,
and partial applications that will sit around forever if we don&amp;rsquo;t complete them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And do we absolutely &lt;em>need&lt;/em> the solid ground of Lambda Calculus or Category
Theory to &lt;em>pre-exist&lt;/em>?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That&amp;rsquo;s an easy one to refute, but these things have become rather holy grail-y
now. If you don&amp;rsquo;t know your monad laws, I&amp;rsquo;m sorry you&amp;rsquo;re not permitted near
functions any more. Oh, and what about proofs? These are in the process of
holy-grailing too&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="is-it-being-declarative">Is it being &amp;ldquo;declarative&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Reduce/ravel/plan/derive/goal-seek?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To be &amp;ldquo;declarative&amp;rdquo; is to want to write down a set of constraints or rules
or input-output relationships, and leave it to the system to figure out not
only &lt;em>what operations&lt;/em> to perform, but also &lt;em>how&lt;/em> and &lt;em>when&lt;/em> to perform them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The declarative world is thrice-removed from the &amp;ldquo;procedural&amp;rdquo; world, where we
have to tell the computer the what, how, and when in excruciating detail.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>SQL, Prolog, APL are seen as &amp;ldquo;highly declarative&amp;rdquo; languages. CSS is also a
highly declarative language (which, I feel, is why people have a really hard
time with it&amp;mdash;CSS is a &lt;em>constraint mechanism&lt;/em> but our minds are strongly
conditioned for procedural thinking).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And maybe AI is the currently-ultimate expression of being &amp;ldquo;declarative&amp;rdquo;. We
declare that we don&amp;rsquo;t even know what to declare, and write a meta-declaration
and hope to Lambda that it will figure out the declaration that we should have
fed to the computer in the first place.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="is-it-being-data-oriented">Is it being &amp;ldquo;data-oriented&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>viz., choosing to work in terms of inert &amp;ldquo;literal&amp;rdquo; entities like JSON or EDN
or XML or some structured binary encoding, instead of &amp;ldquo;live&amp;rdquo; objects with
internal state? Asynchronous message-passing instead of synchronous remote
procedure calls (whether through object graphs, or across computer networks)?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Is it about adhering to the principle of referential transparency; i.e. the
equivalence of evaluated functions and literal data?&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="is-it-about-statelessness">Is it about &amp;ldquo;Statelessness&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>No machine registers? No place-oriented &amp;ldquo;mutable&amp;rdquo; state? No pointers? No
shared references? No side effects? Yes laziness? Yes append-only storage?
Yes event sourcing?&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="is-it-about-managed-environments">Is it about &amp;ldquo;managed&amp;rdquo; environments?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Language mechanisms that relieve us of the burden and perils of malloc/free?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Garbage collection? Immutable persistent data structures? Type-directed
compile-time memory access/use control? Multi-Version Concurrency Control?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Kubernetes?&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="is-it-about-following-some-discipline-and-maybe-automating-it">Is it about following some discipline, and maybe automating it?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>viz. a &lt;em>system&lt;/em> or a design philosophy of doing things, such as:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>An accountant-like state management practice.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Carefully manipulating state only when absolutely necessary.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Hard-wiring FP traits into a programming language / system.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Choosing a strict single-process, non-branching, forward-looping-only
method of flow control.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Having standard, highly general purpose compositional interfaces oriented
around streaming data flow?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Eiffel-like Design-By-Contract? (Which is surprisingly &amp;ldquo;functional&amp;rdquo;.)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Continuation-passing style?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;hellip; etc?&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="my-2-nano-btc-on-the-matter">My 2 nano BTC on the matter&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I think all of our popular programming systems are object-oriented &lt;em>and&lt;/em>
imperative by default, whether explicitly or implicitly. Now they all seem
to be adding &amp;ldquo;functional&amp;rdquo; looking features too. But to me, the functional-ness
of a language (or a system) is not about the feature set, but fundamentally
about its default (automatic) relationship with The State (of the world).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>The &amp;ldquo;Object-Oriented&amp;rdquo; way&lt;/strong> inexorably pushes us to clone reality.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We ingest and manage as much state and behaviour as possible, in order to
emulate the world. This, by construction, requires us to operate based on
theories and assumptions (internal state) doomed to always lag and diverge
from reality. In other words, it&amp;rsquo;s a synchronization problem mixed with the
impossible ideal of wanting to make the actual run-time look like the apparent
run-time. Concurrency quickly reveals the difficulties of trying this.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>The &amp;ldquo;Imperative&amp;rdquo; way&lt;/strong> is more like doing open heart surgery.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We have to get in there and manually orchestrate control flow, interrupt things,
and get the whole of it to mutate in-place &lt;em>while it is running&lt;/em>. The race
condition is always imminent&amp;mdash;will we close first, or will it stop first?
We never &lt;em>really&lt;/em> know if the seemingly routine procedure will cause something
totally unrelated to blow up in our faces this time around. Meanwhile we have
very sharp instruments in hand, and have to do a lot of it by &lt;em>fingerspitzengefühl&lt;/em>
because half the time we literally can&amp;rsquo;t see where to cut or clamp or suture.
I didn&amp;rsquo;t train for this but I hope you have. For at least 10 years. You have,
right? &amp;hellip; Right?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>The &amp;ldquo;Functional&amp;rdquo; way&lt;/strong> wants to completely invert these models.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It tries to expel all system state from inside to the outside. In so doing, it
immerses itself in world-state and tries to be a new conduit for different
parts of outside reality to communicate, hoping to make it behave to our liking.
This, by construction, forces us to think explicitly in terms of events
(discrete sensing and sequencing of world updates, i.e. facts), messaging
(encoding and transmitting facts as data), and time (asynchronicity, consistency,
consensus).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The functional way is also totally different from how we experience the world.
The world is a concurrent, recurrent, parallel, fractal distributed system of
systems. And it is also stochastic and full of discontinuities. We have evolved
to form just-about-good-enough models of reality in our heads, in very bounded
contexts, to the extent necessary for survival. These internal models smooth
over all sorts of discontinuities, resist change while survival odds feel good,
and determine how we behave regardless of what might actually be out there.
We learn imperatively by poking and prodding the world around us while it hums
along. I think this is why it takes serious effort to learn the &amp;ldquo;functional&amp;rdquo;
way. We have to upend our entire mental model of how to do things in the world.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Maybe pure data at rest&lt;/strong> is the only truly &amp;ldquo;functional&amp;rdquo; thing?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Maybe not. Like a pure function, pure data at rest does nothing and so is
useless to us when dormant. Besides, it is &amp;ldquo;pure&amp;rdquo; &lt;em>only&lt;/em> for the duration
entropy permits its complete un-corrupted recovery. Ultimately, the laws of
Physics will always win. To muddy the waters a bit more, even the purest of
pure functional systems contain state; signals in flight or some in-progress
computation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The only saving grace is that in a highly functional system, any run-time
state is entirely recoverable, reproducible, discrete, and isolated.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>All said, everything mutates sooner or later.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I don&amp;rsquo;t know how to navigate this, except to remind myself about The Thing
That Actually Matters&amp;hellip; to always remember that The State is the frenemy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So while it pleases me that so many wish to eagerly embrace the Functional Way,
it is good to be soberly mindful of scopes, lifetimes, margins, error budgets,
and bounds of reality (state) and of data (information about reality). Good
situational awareness will lead us to build highly functional systems that
keep The State where it belongs, and still do useful things with it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And all &lt;em>that&lt;/em> said, I leave you with this prayer:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4">&lt;code class="language-text" data-lang="text">O Lambda the Ultimate,
bless the reader of these words.
That their core be functional,
and their functions be pure.
That their data be immutable,
so they may know the value of values.
That their systems be composable,
so they may grow and scale with grace.
That their States only mutate
in pleasantly surprising ways.
For otherwise nothing lives.
Nothing evolves.
In the name of the alpha,
the beta, and the eta...
(λx.x x) (λx.x x)
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div></content></item><item><title>Baby don't hurry, don't stop (feat. Melancholy)</title><link>/posts/dont-hurry-dont-stop-sad-version/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2022 10:24:39 +0530</pubDate><guid>/posts/dont-hurry-dont-stop-sad-version/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is how I struggle from time to time. It is not pretty. These days it&amp;rsquo;s
been a lot more. Thankfully, it is not a constant. Instead of reading this,
you should want to listen to Alain de Botton.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Aw1oLtuJOXQ">on Pessimism&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jJ6K%5Ff7oSdg">on Love&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=W9X7u-MeJz0">on an Emotional Education&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>For here lies melancholy that I put to paper from a particularly deep hole,
not too long ago. It may ruin your day, or it may make you feel a little bit
understood about your dark moments. And it&amp;mdash;unlike Alain&amp;rsquo;s teachings&amp;mdash;will
certainly not help you find a way through.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Your mileage &lt;em>will&lt;/em> vary.&lt;/p></description><content>&lt;p>This is how I struggle from time to time. It is not pretty. These days it&amp;rsquo;s
been a lot more. Thankfully, it is not a constant. Instead of reading this,
you should want to listen to Alain de Botton.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Aw1oLtuJOXQ">on Pessimism&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jJ6K%5Ff7oSdg">on Love&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=W9X7u-MeJz0">on an Emotional Education&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>For here lies melancholy that I put to paper from a particularly deep hole,
not too long ago. It may ruin your day, or it may make you feel a little bit
understood about your dark moments. And it&amp;mdash;unlike Alain&amp;rsquo;s teachings&amp;mdash;will
certainly not help you find a way through.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Your mileage &lt;em>will&lt;/em> vary.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Today was one of those days.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When the feeling hit like a slap in the face. Again. Just how much of my
youth burned in self-doubt, fear, self-shame, akrasia.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Twenty years of young adulthood incinerated by mine own hand, before my own
eyes, and I did nothing to save it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sigh.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This life is singular. It is not ours to have. It is not ours to end. It is
ours to embrace as a gift to give away.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The gift is a chance to become all that we can become. We cannot become, if we
keep staring down at ourselves from imagined imaginations of others. What if
I can&amp;rsquo;t do it? What if I fail? What if nobody likes me? I am not &lt;em>this&lt;/em>. I am
not &lt;em>that&lt;/em>. I&amp;rsquo;ll never get &lt;em>there&lt;/em>. &lt;em>I&lt;/em> am not even someone. That is the root
of all self-doubt and fear and shame. A never-being in the here and now. A
never-learning about oneself. A never-knowing of feeling alive. The kind of
poverty that material things cannot end.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Looking from the outside makes us pressure and twist ourselves into the imagined
mould. But the mould changes before we&amp;rsquo;re done. And we start again. The cycle is
endless, relentless. We go faster, but it changes faster. And we forget ourselves.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If there is one gift we can give to another, especially a young one, it would
be to show them how to live this: &amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t hurry, don&amp;rsquo;t stop.&amp;rdquo;. To learn to &lt;em>do&lt;/em>,
without fearing the unknown, knowing failure without shame, with kindness, with
oneself, without hurry.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Hurry forces pause. Not pausing breaks us. So many break forever. Never becoming.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So many learn too late, that they only know to hurry, that they can&amp;rsquo;t slow down.
Once perhaps, long ago, they peered inside their mould and saw nothing. It&amp;rsquo;s
not that nothing exists, it&amp;rsquo;s that they never learned to see. And so all that
remained was to dwell in the future; remoulding faster and faster until the
breakdown. Or worse, to delve into the past, in endless revisions of discarded
moulds to reach an imagined now that never will come to pass. If there is a
metaverse, it is this.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This prisoners' game of imagined imaginations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Fantasies rooted in fantasy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s not too late for you. Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s not too late for me.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I hope it isn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But if it is too late, then I hope we come back, you and I.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For a rebirth requires a death.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;em>“It is better to do something continuously, perpetually and untiringly than to hustle and fail.”&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>“If you hurry, you must rest. If you want to keep going without resting, then you mustn’t hurry.”&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>“Don’t hurry, don’t stop”&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kintar%C5%8D%5FHattori">Kintarō Hattori&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote></content></item><item><title>How To Be a Totally Natural Conference Speaker?</title><link>/posts/how-to-give-a-conference-talk/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2022 01:56:02 +0530</pubDate><guid>/posts/how-to-give-a-conference-talk/</guid><description>&lt;p>A friend and I were chatting recently about speaking at conferences. Now this
person is smart and I&amp;rsquo;ve learned a thing or two from his in-depth engineering
blog posts. Yet there he was, telling me I&amp;rsquo;m so super good at communicating
ideas (implying he&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>not&lt;/em> so super good), and besides he has nothing to say
worthy of a conference talk.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Huh?!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Uncalled for praise is jarring, but I took it&amp;mdash;2021 was heartless, OK? Still,
the subtext of &lt;em>magic&lt;/em> bothered me. That I am somehow special. A born natural.
So I told him my secret formula. And now I&amp;rsquo;m telling you.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here is how to be a totes natural conference speaker&amp;hellip;&lt;/p></description><content>&lt;p>A friend and I were chatting recently about speaking at conferences. Now this
person is smart and I&amp;rsquo;ve learned a thing or two from his in-depth engineering
blog posts. Yet there he was, telling me I&amp;rsquo;m so super good at communicating
ideas (implying he&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>not&lt;/em> so super good), and besides he has nothing to say
worthy of a conference talk.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Huh?!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Uncalled for praise is jarring, but I took it&amp;mdash;2021 was heartless, OK? Still,
the subtext of &lt;em>magic&lt;/em> bothered me. That I am somehow special. A born natural.
So I told him my secret formula. And now I&amp;rsquo;m telling you.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here is how to be a totes natural conference speaker&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Mope around &lt;em>all the time&lt;/em> about how you don&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em>really&lt;/em> know [Topic X].
Sooner or later an opportune Call For Proposals will slide into your Twitter
stream or Slack or Discord. (It is very important to mope around &lt;em>all&lt;/em> the
time. Also, please cultivate several topics to mope around about. This
guarantees that every moment is an opportune moment to propose a talk.)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Foolishly jump at the chance. Write a proposal to talk (or teach a class)
about said [Topic X].&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Congratulations! You have now made a public commitment, and opted into the
specter of falling flat on your face before all and sundry. Let the feeling
sink in.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>When it does, panic and feel obligated to start making something already,
because what if you can&amp;rsquo;t actually figure out [Topic X]? Because then you
must recuse yourself before it&amp;rsquo;s too late. Proceed to have trouble starting,
toss and turn in bed many nights in a row, and finally start typing
something&amp;mdash;anything&amp;mdash;into your computer.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Make and trash at least 3 shitty first drafts. Feel like an impostor and
&lt;em>almost&lt;/em> withdraw your proposal as many times.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>If your proposal gets selected, GOTO 3 and start over. If it doesn&amp;rsquo;t, GOTO 8.
If you are back here after the do-over, GOTO 7. If you got here and you don&amp;rsquo;t
know why, well that&amp;rsquo;s because GOTOs are Considered Harmful.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Somehow arrive at a version you don&amp;rsquo;t totally hate. Then make minor edits
and tweaks for days and days until you&amp;rsquo;re fed up. (Actually you are fed up
because the talk is just a week away by now, and you haven&amp;rsquo;t rehearsed even
once.)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Corral friends who are way smarter than you, and get them to hear you out.
(Actually there&amp;rsquo;s a step zero. Get very lucky in life and land up with such
friends).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Listen to them and don&amp;rsquo;t make any more edits.&lt;/em> Seriously. Try to rehearse.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Second-guess yourself 48 hours before your talk, mid-way through your first
&lt;em>actual&lt;/em> rehearsal. Proceed to commit the cardinal sin of refactoring the
whole bloody thing &amp;ldquo;before shipping to production&amp;rdquo;, because apparently it&amp;rsquo;s
all completely &lt;em>wrong&lt;/em> now. Don&amp;rsquo;t sleep much, of course.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Wake up with a start on D-day. Curse at yourself in the mirror. Drink an
unconscionable quantity of coffee, while feverishly reviewing your material.
Entirely miss the &amp;ldquo;hallway track&amp;rdquo; and fail to make new friends or to have
a good time.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Somehow make it to the other end of your presentation. It&amp;rsquo;s OK, everybody
forgets half the material (especially those painstakingly crafted turns of
phrase and clever asides), and still somehow runs out of time. Spend the
rest of the day in a growing fog because the adrenaline wore off, but the
caffeine didn&amp;rsquo;t, but you&amp;rsquo;re wiped-out from the excitement and sleep-deprived.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Luckily, that also means you forget everything you did on your talk day.
Now you just have to make sure you never ever watch the recording of your
talk, if they publish it.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Bask in the certain knowledge that you too have become a 100% Totally Natural
Conference Speaker. (As a veteran of this process, I can tell you it works.
Every. Single. Time.)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Jokes apart, it really is like that. There is no magic. Only student syndrome.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Just remember that you always know more about something than someone, and/or
almost certainly have a &lt;em>different, unique take&lt;/em> on something that you believe
to be common knowledge. Not infrequently, I find someone&amp;rsquo;s interpretation of
something I am intimately familiar with, and the interpretation remarkably
changes how I see/feel/understand/relate with the thing. (Frequently it does
not, and it&amp;rsquo;s rubbish, but that&amp;rsquo;s fine. I&amp;rsquo;m not the one for that one.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Why? Well because no topic is objectively too small or too silly or too useless,
for the right audience in the right context.
Look no further than &lt;a href="https://bangbangcon.com/program.html">!!Con&lt;/a>, for example.
People have i!!ega! amounts of fun there!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So do yourself a favour. Allow yourself chances to suggest your [Topic X] to
the world, even when it&amp;rsquo;s just your take on your favourite thing that maybe
everybody already knows. Because maybe the world will say&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Sure, why not?&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>